Finding aid for Interlochen Center for The Arts Records, 1927-2005
Bentley Historical Library
- Chronological, 1920-1966
  - Subject Files, 1928-1989
    - Maddy
      - Broadcasting
        "Broadcasting", mainly 1931-1948, documents Maddy's non-Interlochen radio work. It includes his correspondence and scripts for instrumental and vocal education programs as well as correspondence, reports, and other records on his attempt to create an alternative to commercial radio, largely using the new FM technology. Scripts include those used by announcers Mike Wallace and Ward Quaal and texts of radio addresses on Americanism by Murray Van Wagoner, Leo Fitzpatrick, and Karl Detzer. Researchers will also want to check "Civic Music" for Maddy's wartime broadcasts and "Music Education" for the professional educators' program "Music and American Youth." Since much of his non-Interlochen broadcasting was done for the university, reports and other information about it can be found under "University of Michigan" (6) in this sub-subseries. Recordings and a movie film of his instructional programs can be found in the Visual Materials and Sound Recordings series.
        - University of Michigan radio, 1931-1954
          - History (Box 16)
          - General
            - Papers, 1931-1954; 8 folders (Box 16)
            - U. of M. student papers, circa, 1935-1936 (Box 16)
            - Summer survey responses, 1937 (Box 16)
            - W.P.A.-student workers, 1938-1940 (Box 16)
          - Program materials
            - Band & gen'l instrument lessons
              - February and March, including course book, 1931 (Box 16)
              - February and March, 1932
                - Announcements and scripts (Box 16)
                - Survey of participating schools (Box 16)
                - Correspondence (Box 16)
              - October-December-course book, 1932 (Box 16)
              - 1933-1935-scripts and lesson plans, 2 folders (Box 16)
              - 1935-1936
                (WJR and WMAQ)
                - Correspondence
                - Production (mainly NBC) (Box 16)
                - General (Box 16)
                - Instruction book orders (Box 16)
                - Participating schools, circa, 1936 (Box 16)
                - Scripts, 2 folders (Box 16)
                - Network plans for "Musical Youth" (Box 16)
              - (NBC) "Fun in Music", 1936-1937
                - Correspondence
                - Production (mainly NBC) (Box 16)
                - General, 2 folders (Box 16)
                - Listener (Box 16)
                - Script drafts, 1936 (Box 16)
                - Scripts and lesson plans, 2 folders (Box 16)
              - (NBC) "Fun in Music", 1937-1938
                - Correspondence-general (Box 16)
                - Promotional materials (Box 16)
                - Scripts and lesson plans, 2 folders (Box 16)
              - (NBC) "Music Makers", 1938-1939
                - Correspondence-NBC (Box 17)
                - Scripts and lesson plans, 2 folders (Box 17)
              - Scripts (partial), 1936-1939 (Box 17)
              - 1939-re possible CBS pick-up (Box 17)
            - String lessons
              - History (1933-1937) (Box 17)
              - Scripts and school list, 1933-1934 (Box 17)
              - Scripts, 1934-1936; 2 folders (Box 17)
              - Letter and scripts, 1936-1937 (Box 17)
              - Lesson outlines, 1950-1951 (Box 17)
              - Wisconsin radio interest, 1950-1951 (Box 17)
            - Singing lessons
              - Scripts, 1933-1936 (Box 17)
              - Correspondence and scripts, 1938-1939 (Box 17)
              - Correspondence and scripts, 1940-1941 (Box 17)
            - Hymn program
              - History (Box 17)
              - Correspondence and scripts, 1936-1937 (Box 17)
              - Correspondence, 1937-1938 (Box 17)
              - 1938-1939
                - CBS correspondence (Box 17)
                - General correspondence and scripts (Box 17)
              - Scripts, 1939-1940 (Box 17)
              - Correspondence and scripts, 1940-1944; 2 folders (Box 17)
              - Hymn reference files (alpha), circa, 1942 (Box 17)
              - Later hymn correspondence, 1946-1958 (Box 17)
            - Patriotic, "Why Save Democracy", 1941 (Box 17)
            - Music instruction (general)
              - Correspondence, 1935-1947 (Box 17)
            - Recordings
              - RCA Victor, 1935-1939 (Box 17)
              - Script, circa, 1936 (Box 17)
            - Evaluation of School Broadcasts (Ohio State University), including "Fun in Music,", 1937-1939 (Box 17)
          - Educational Broadcasting
            - General
              - NBC letter and Maddy FCC statement, 1934 (Box 17)
              - Correspondence, 1935-1958 (Box 17)
              - Conference materials, 1934-1938 (Box 17)
              - Miscellaneous printed, 1934-1940 (Box 17)
            - Network
              - History (Box 17)
              - Initial effort (Wiesner, Charters, and Maddy), 1938-1939 (Box 17)
              - Association for Education by Radio
                - 1942 (Box 17)
                (founding as branch of NEA)
                - 1943 (Box 17)
                (Michigan chapter organized at Interlochen)
              - FM radio Network
                - 1943-1944, 4 folders (Box 17)
                - 1945-1948, 4 folders (Box 18)
            - National Academy of Broadcasting Foundation, 1949-1950 (Box 18)
            - Educational television, 1958-1962 (Box 18)
          - Miscellaneous
            - Articles by Maddy, 1931-1938 (Box 18)
            - Articles by others on Maddy, 1934-1935 (Box 18)
            - Maddy talks, 1931-1947 (Box 18)
            - Maddy talks, WPAG (Ann Arbor), 1947 (Box 18)
            - Ann Arbor Broadcasting Co., 1937-1939 (Box 18)
            - NBC-television, 1939 (Box 18)
            - Miscellaneous printed, 1939-1946 (Box 18)
      - Civic music
        "Civic Music" (1939-1961) includes correspondence, programs, reports, and other materials on Maddy's adult orchestra endeavors, including the wartime civic music program. Its coverage begins with the organizing conference for National Civic Music at the Camp and continues with his directorship of the Ann Arbor Civic Orchestra Association and Michigan Civic Music Association, especially the latter's massed orchestra performances. The Wartime Civic Music materials cover his appearances and broadcasts, his battle with publishers over production of a patriotic songbook for public use, and his solicitation of new musical works with a patriotic theme.
        - National Civic Music Conference (at Interlochen), 1939-1940; 4 folders (Box 18)
        - Ann Arbor Civic (Symphony) Orchestra, 1940-1961; 6 folders (Box 18)
        - Michigan Civic Music Association, 1941-1961
          - History (Box 18)
          - Papers, 1941-1961, 4 folders (Box 18)
          - American Symphony Orchestra League, 1946 (Box 18)
        - Wartime Civic Music
          - Music Industries War Council, 1942 (Box 18)
          - Michigan Council of Defense
            - Papers, 1942 (Box 18)
            - Leadership lists, 1942-1943 (Box 18)
            - Newsletter, 1942-1944 (Box 18)
          - National materials, circa, 1942-1943 (Box 18)
          - Conference on Civic Music and the War Effort, 1942 (Box 18)
          - Committee on Wartime Civic Music
            - State, 1942-1945; 7 folders (Box 18)
            - Local, 1942-1943
              - Organizational materials, 1942
                - Ann Arbor (Box 18)
                - Other communities (Box 18)
              - Programs, 1942-1943 (Box 18)
            - Newspaper articles, 1942-1943 (Box 18)
            - Articles by Maddy, circa, 1942-1943 (Box 18)
            - Battle Songs of Freedom
              - Planning materials (Box 19)
              - Publishers' copyright, 1942-1943 (Box 19)
              - Miscellaneous printed, 1940-1943 (Box 19)
            - Broadcasts
              - Correspondence, 1942-1943 (Box 19)
              - WJR (Detroit) scripts, 1942 (Box 19)
              - WKAR (E. Lansing) scripts, 1943 (Box 19)
            - Historical pageant scripts, circa, 1943 (Box 19)
            - Marching songs-response to appeal for, 1942-1945; 2 folders (Box 19)
          - Travel (Maddy), 1942-1943 (Box 19)
      - Music education, 1921-1966
        "Music Education" (1921-1966), contains Maddy's correspondence on general developments in the field and on his work with professional organizations. The former mainly concerns responses to inquiries. He deals with overall trends, such as the decline of school orchestras and the need for string instruction, as well as elaborating on teaching techniques for specific instruments. Correspondence of a similar nature with leading music educators can be found in Chronology Special Correspondence and with radio listeners in Subject Interlochen-Broadcasting. The string workshop which he taught at Interlochen is documented in Subject Camp under "Course Materials."
        His major professional work for the Music Educators National Conference (MENC), 1921-1966, begins with background information on orchestra and band contests and festivals. It continues with his work arranging student performances for the 1933 Century of Progress Exhibition in Chicago (where he first came into conflict with Petrillo). It also covers his leadership of the Research Council, particularly the publication on Music Rooms and Equipment (including its proposed revisions).
        Records on his presidency and executive committee service follow as do those on his Broadcast Committee leadership, including the MENC national radio program, "Music and American Youth," 1938-1940 (where he again ran into problems with Petrillo). The section concludes with records covering the remainder of his relations with the MENC, including its support of efforts for a postwar youth orchestra tour of Europe and its 1959 meeting at the Camp. His reaction to the MENC leadership agreement with Petrillo (1947) can be found in the series Subject Interlochen "Petrillo" and in the Giddings and Tremaine correspondence of Chronological Camp files, 1945-1966. The archives of the MENC are preserved at the McKeldin Library of the University of Maryland.
        His other professional activities include service on the National Committee for Music in Education, 1938-1940, which lobbied for creation of a Fine Arts Division within the U.S. Department of Education. For organizations associated with Interlochen (institutional support or membership), researchers should consult Subject Interlochen "Organizations" in this series.
        - History
          - General (by Maddy) (Box 19)
          - Reminiscences of a music educator, Frederick Fennell, 1963 (Box 19)
        - General correspondence, 1930-1965; 4 folders (Box 19)
        - Miscellaneous papers
          - Sokoloff's suggested closing of music schools, 1935 (Box 19)
          - Use of movies (Eyes on America), 1940 (Box 19)
          - String instruction, 1948-1951 (Box 19)
          - Use of recordings (Wilcox-Gay Corp.), 1946-1947 (Box 19)
        - Music Educators National Conference (MENC)
          - Convention programs, 1921-1936 (Box 19)
          - Committee on Instrumental Affairs
            - Contests and festivals
              - History (Box 19)
              - Correspondence and papers, 1927-1944; 7 folders (Box 19)
              - Program and informational materials
                - National, 1927-1939; 3 folders (Box 19)
                - Michigan, 1927-1934 (Box 19)
            - Publications, 1926-1934; undated (Box 19)
            - Century of Progress (Chicago), 1932-1933
              - Planning materials (Box 19)
              - Correspondence regarding group appearances, 3 folders (Box 20)
              - Michigan Day papers (Box 20)
          - Research Council
            - General, 1933-1937 (Box 20)
            - Music Rooms and Equipment
              - Report, 1934-1936 (Box 20)
              - Proposed revisions, 1938-1945; 1955 (Box 20)
          - Pre-presidential miscellanea
            - General, 1934-1935 (Box 20)
            - Committee on Music and Leisure Time, 1934 (Box 20)
          - Presidential, 1936-1938
            - Address-"Teaching Music by Radio,", 1936 (Box 20)
            - General-including effort to secure a Fine Arts Division in the U. S. Department of Education, 1936-1938; 2 folders (Box 20)
            - St. Louis convention
              - Planning, 1936-1938 (Box 20)
              - Program, 1938 (Box 20)
              - Printed materials, 1938 (Box 20)
            - Journal articles by Maddy, 1936-1938 (Box 20)
          - Broadcast (Radio) Committee
            - Code of Ethics-proposed (American Federation of Musicians), 1937 (Box 20)
            - "Music and American Youth", 1938-1940; 5 folders (Box 20)
            - Montana Civic Broadcasting, 1940 (Box 20)
            - Miscellaneous, 1938-1940 (Box 20)
          - Post-presidential
            - General, including Executive Committee, 1938-1948; 6 folders (Box 20)
            - North Central Conference, 1938-1948 (Box 20)
            - General, including President's Council, 1952-1959; 2 folders (Box 20)
            - Interlochen meeting, 1959 (Box 21)
            - General, 1960-1966 (Box 21)
          - Other organizations
            - Michigan Music Teachers Association, 1962-1963 (Box 21)
            - Michigan School Band and Orchestra Association, 1942-1947 (Box 21)
            - Music Teachers National Association, 1939-1957 (Box 21)
            - National Committee for Music in Education, 1938-1940 (Box 21)
      - Publications, Speeches, and Writings, 1920-1968
        "Publications, Speeches, and Writings"(1920-1968) subsection includes Maddy's correspondence with publishers and collaborators, drafts of his works, articles by and about him, his music education publications, and his music arrangements. Many of his articles were publicity pieces for the Camp. His other publications were largely instructional in nature, both individual and group. His musical arrangements, including for Howard Hanson, reflect his extensive activity in the field. His few attempts at composition are included with them. Maddy's relationship with ASCAP is documented, but researchers interested in its association with the Camp should also check Subject Interlochen "Organizations."
        - Articles
          - Interlochen related
            - Correspondence, 1940-1963 (Box 21)
            - Drafts, 1928-1965; undated; 2 folders (Box 21)
            - Printed, 1940-1964 (Box 21)
          - General (largely music education)
            - Correspondence, 1936-1964 (Box 21)
            - "History of School Music" (for The Instrumentalist) correspondence and drafts, 1955 (Box 21)
            - Drafts, 1920-1966; 6 folders (Box 21)
            - Printed, 1920-1964; 2 folders (Box 21)
        - Speeches (note cards)
          - Delivered outside Interlochen, 1961-1966 (Box 21)
          - Delivered at Camp, 1963-1965 (Box 21)
          - Delivered at Academy, 1963-1965 (Box 21)
          - Miscellanea, circa, 1950s-1960s (Box 21)
        - Musical works
          - Bibliographies (Box 21)
          - American Society of Composers, Authors and Publishers, 1935-1962 (Box 21)
          - Publishers correspondence
            - American Book Company, 1935-1939 (Box 21)
            - Birchard, C.C., 1935-1941 (Box 21)
            - Chappell and Company, 1939-1940 (Box 21)
            - Fischer, Carl, 1935-1955 (Box 21)
            - Hall & McCreary, 1937-1959 (Box 21)
            - Kjos, Neil A., 1941-1960 (Box 21)
            - Music Publishers Holding Corp., 1938-1940 (Box 21)
            - Pioneer Music Press, 1958-1959 (Box 22)
            - Willis Music, 1936-1952 (Box 22)
            - Wurlitzer, 1935-1947 (Box 22)
            - Miscellaneous, 1940-1941 (Box 22)
          - Publisher royalty statements, 1937-1939 (Box 22)
          - Collaborators correspondence
            - Church, Norval L., 1945-1947 (Box 22)
            - Miessner, W. Otto, 1942-1943 (Box 22)
            - Watters, Lorrain, 1939-1941 (Box 22)
            - Miscellaneous, 1943 (Box 22)
          - Published instructional materials
            - List of unique items retained by Interlochen (Box 22)
            - 1924
              - Willis Graded School Orchestra and Band Series-with Giddings (Box 22)
            - 1926
              - Willis Graded School Orchestra and Band Series-with Giddings (Box 22)
              - Instrumental Technique for Orchestras and Band (Willis)-with Giddings (Box 22)
              - Universal Teacher (Willis)-with Giddings (Box 22)
            - 1927
              - Standard Orchestra Folio (Irving Berlin Standard Music Corp.) (Box 22)
              - Willis Instrumental Quartet Repertoire-with Giddings (Box 23)
            - 1928
              - Willis Graded Orchestra and Band Series-with Giddings (Box 23)
            - 1929
              - School Bands: How They May Be Developed (Box 23)
            - 1930
              - All-State High School Orchestras (National Bureau for the Advancement of Music) (Box 23)
              - The Classic and Modern Band Book (Presser)-with Wilfred Wilson (Box 23)
              - Modern School Graded Orchestra Books (Fischer)-with Charles J. Roberts (Box 23)
              - Trione Folio (Fischer)-with Giddings and Roberts (Box 23)
            - 1931
              - Michigan University of the Air, band instrument course book (Willis) (Box 23)
            - 1933
              - Radio Music Course for Band ...and...Stringed Instruments (Edwards Bros.) (Box 23)
            - 1937
              - Fun in Music (American Book Company)-with Giddings (Box 23)
            - 1938
              - Symphonic Band Folio (Fischer) (Box 24)
            - 1943
              - All-American Song Book (Robbins)-with Miessner (Box 24)
            - 1948
              - Symphonic String Course (Kjos), unfinished ms. oversized (Box 84)
          - Miscellaneous instructional
            - Manuscript, Interlochen Band Method, undated (Box 24)
            - Mimeographed, The Interlochen Music Course, developed by the Interlochen Honors Musicianship Project, H.E.W. grant #253, directed by Maddy, assisted by others, 1965-1968 (Box 24)
          - Arrangements and compositions
            - Listing, undated (Box 24)
            - Correspondence, 1938-1955 (Box 24)
            - Pieces (ms. and printed)
              - The Lost Chord (Willis), 1937 (Box 24)
              - Army and Navy March (Willis), 1938 (Box 24)
              - Camp-Fire March (Willis), 1938 (Box 24)
              - The Counselor (Willis) Maddy, 1938 (Box 24)
              - Nordic Symphony (Birchard) Howard Hanson, 1938 (Box 24)
              - Arabian Nights (Chappell) Allen Grant, 1939 (Box 24)
              - Jungle Land Suite (Chappell) Allen Grant, 1939 (Box 24)
              - Marco Polo Suite (Chappell) Allen Grant, 1939 (Box 24)
              - Paul Bunyan's Suite (Chappell) Allen Grant, 1939 (Box 24)
              - Paul Revere Suite (Chappell) Allen Grant, 1939 (Box 24)
              - Southland Symphony (ms.) Allen Grant, 1939 (Box 24)
              - Prayer and Dream Pantomime (Remick) Engelbert Humperdinck, 1943 (Box 24)
              - In Balladenton (ms.) Grieg, 1946 (Box 24)
              - Festival Finale (Kjos) traditional hymns arranged for dedication of Kresge Auditorium, 1949; unfinished ms.,oversize (Box 84)
              - Quartet, opus 30, undated, Tschaikowski (Box 24)
              - Themes from Symphony No. l, undated, Sibelius (Box 24)
      - University of Michigan
        "University of Michigan" (1930-1949) relates to Maddy's work for the university. It contains correspondence concerning his travels throughout the state under the auspices of the Extension Service, his university appointment forms, and his reports to university superiors. Included is a 1932 survey by the Extension Service of "School Contests and Festivals in Michigan." Other U. of M. materials can be found in Maddy "Broadcasting" and Interlochen "University of Michigan" in this series.
        - Reports and correspondence, 1930-1954; 8 folders (Box 25)
        - Extension service survey of contests and festivals, 1935
          - Summary results (Box 25)
          - Individual school responses, A-Z, 4 folders (Box 25)
    - Giddings and Tremaine
      The Giddings and Tremaine sub-subseries features biographical information on and publications by the other two early leaders of the Camp. The Giddings portion, 1907-1953, contains largely his manuscript and printed writings: radio scripts (for instructional programs), speeches, articles, texts, and life reminiscences. Tremaine's section, 1932-1962, includes publications, reports, and some correspondence, relating mainly to his work with the National Bureau for Advancement of Music (NBAM).
      - Giddings
        - Biographical (Box 25)
        - McDermid dissertation, Maddy and Stace correspondence re, 1965-1966 (Box 25)
        - Writings (manuscript)
          - Reminiscences, 1923; 1940; undated (Box 25)
          - Music speeches and articles, 1926-1937; undated; 3 folders (Box 25)
          - Interlochen article, undated (Box 25)
          - Non-music articles, 1934-1935; undated (Box 25)
          - Radio scripts, "Music for Every Child," WDGY (Minneapolis), 1939-1940 (Box 25)
          - Draft for text on music instruction, circa 1951 based on earlier publication for Minneapolis schools, undated (Box 25)
        - Publications (printed)
          - Public School Class Method for the Piano, 1919 (Box 25)
          - Grade School Music Teaching (text), 1919 (Box 25)
          - Songs of Childhood, Music Education Series, 1923 (Box 25)
          - Articles
            - School Music Monthly, 1907-1914 (Box 25)
            - Other, 1922-1933 (Box 25)
        - Miscellaneous printed
          - Minneapolis public schools, 1915-1948 (Box 25)
          - Other, 1934; 1945 (Box 25)
      - Tremaine
        - Biographical (Box 26)
        - Writings (mainly printed)
          - Brochure, 1934 (Box 26)
          - Published articles, 1936-1954 (Box 26)
        - National Bureau for Advancement of Music
          - Reports and correspondence, 1922-1934 (Box 26)
          - National Music Week (printed), 1937-1977 (Box 26)
          - School Band and Orchestra Contests, 1924-1932 (Box 26)
          - Other publications, 1924-1942 (Box 26)
    - Interlochen (Camp and Academy)
      The Interlochen sub-subseries covers topics relevant to the institution in general, mainly under Maddy but also under his successors until 1989. The sub-subseries has been further divided into seventeen subsections: (1) Alumni, (2) Broadcasting, (3) Campus, (4) Financial, (5) Fund Raising/Development, (6) Interlochen Arts Festival, (7) Interlochen Press, (8) International, (9) International Society of Music Educators, (10) Michigan, (11) Organizations, (12) Petrillo Controversy, (13) Publicity/Promotion, (14) Special Events and Programs, (15) Traverse City, (16) United States Government, and (17) University of Michigan. Materials before 1962 usually relate to the Camp, and thereafter, to both the Camp and Academy. The files often document activities which Maddy initiated, but which were subsequently handled by others.
      - Alumni